<?xml version="1.0"?>
<blogs>
  <blog>
    <thumbnail>https://static.wixstatic.com/media/nsplsh_4372446e4551455f397659~mv2_d_4288_2848_s_4_2.jpg/v1/fill/w_285,h_214,fp_0.50_0.50,q_90,enc_auto/nsplsh_4372446e4551455f397659~mv2_d_4288_2848_s_4_2.webp</thumbnail>
    <title>How Do I Get Kings Canyon and Sequoia National Park Backpacking Permits?</title>
    <link>https://www.pathloom.com/post/how-to-get-a-backpacking-permit-sequoia-national-park</link>
    <date>Nov 5</date>
    <content>Elon Jones
Nov 5
6 min read
How Do I Get Kings Canyon and Sequoia National Park Backpacking Permits?
There’s something amazing about the sight of tall trees – like super tall trees. We’re talking trees as tall as skyscrapers that are miles away from any metropolis — the Sequoias. 

If you’re craving lush forests that are so high they block the clouds, stark mountains and grassy foothills that remind you how small you are, then Sequoia and Kings Canyon National Parks are for you.

First though, you have to sort out Sequoia National Park backpacking permits and routes. 

We navigated the wilderness permit process for Sequoia National Park and – with the help of our trusty Permit Strategy Guide – we’re laying out how to get Kings Canyon and Sequoia National Park backpacking permits, so you can stand in awe behind a canopy of Sequoias.

Nature has a way of reminding us how small we are. 
Key Insights

The best time to visit Kings Canyon and Sequoia National Park is during spring and summer, but it’s easier to get permits starting in September and running until May.
During Quota season, you can apply for a permit from 6 months in advance to a week before your desired date.
From September to May there are no quotas, and you can self-issue a permit at any of the permit issuing stations.
Walk-Up Permits are available when a group doesn’t show up to claim their permit on time.
Climbing Mount Whitney from via Sequoia National Park requires a separate permit.

When Is the Best Time to Visit Sequoia National Park?

Sequoia National Park’s busy season falls roughly between the end of May and the end of September, which inevitably means there are quotas in place to prevent overcrowding.

From May to September is the best time to visit the park because you can access all areas without fear of snow. The spring and summer months’ moderate temperatures and clear skies make for a picturesque setting for your backpacking trip, while colder temperatures mean more cozy campfire stories. Picture all of the fun things you want to do there — meandering through endless forest trails, camping under the stars. 

From the end of September to the following May, there’s no quota, which means you can pick up permits at the Wilderness Permit Desks at the trailhead nearest to your entry point the day before or the day of your entry. 

How Do I Get Sequoia Backpacking Permits?



During the non-quota season, it’s straight forward. 

Between the end of September and the end of May, obtaining your permit depends on which trailhead you want to take. 

There are five wilderness permit stations where you can pick up your permit. These permits are free and self-issued. That means it’s up to you to provide a detailed itinerary to the rangers in case of an emergency. The stations provide them, you fill them out and continue on your journey.

If you’re visiting during quota season, you can apply up to six months and in as little as one week before your trip. Reservations are released every day at 7 am PST. You can see online whether there’s availability for the size of your group and the dates you want to visit.

During quota season, permits cost $15 and $5 per person in your group if your application is accepted. We hope you get that lucky acceptance email in your inbox!

More permits become available if parties don’t show up by 10:00 am in the morning on the day of their hike, which are redistributed on a first-come, first-serve basis. That means you can get one of these walk-up permits by being at the stations at 1:00 pm, ready to accept what someone else threw away.

What Other Permits and Passes Do I Need?



If all you plan to do is backpack, then the only other permit you need – beside the wilderness permit for Sequoia and Kings Canyon – is the campfire permit. Check the fire restrictions in the park before reserving your campfire permit, which is free and must be printed for your trip.

You can see all of the activities that require extra permits here. 

As far as fees go, there is an entry fee to Sequoia National Park. You can either get a one-time pass or an annual America the Beautiful Pass for $80. And yes, there are discounts for children and seniors as well.

There are no permits for any specific trailheads, mountain climbs, or hikes. So enjoy climbs like Little Baldy, Angel Wings, Grand Sentinel, and more to your heart’s desire. But keep in mind that, throughout the summer, certain routes on Moro Rock and Chimney Rock close to protect peregrine falcons during their nesting season. 

Mount Whitney, on the other hand, is a special case which we’ll discuss below. 

Climbing Mount Whitney via Sequoia National Park

Mount Whitney is the most popular mountain in the Sierra Nevadas. Overnight backpackers as well as day hikers need a permit to access the region’s towering heights. 

Pro Tip from the Pathloom Permit Strategy Guide: There are two ways to access Mount Whitney, so if you miss out on a permit from one place you can try for it through the other.

Many backpackers begin in Sequoia National Park, so a Mount Whitney permit from there gives you full access to the trails leading up to Mount Whitney. But if you can’t get a permit from Sequoia, you could also choose to start from Inyo National Forest. You’ll just need to get a permit from Inyo instead. 

The route to reach Mount Whitney from Sequoia National Park takes more time and has more challenging trails. The National Park Service estimates that it takes 10 days to get there and come back. If this sounds like a fun challenge, this might be the best route for you.

Which Is Better, Sequoia National Park or Sequoia National Forest? 

This truly depends on what you want to see on your trip. Let’s start with Sequoia National Forest.

Sequoia National Forest covers over a million acres of California and has dozens of campgrounds and trailheads to choose from. You will need a permit for camping in Golden Trout Wilderness, but they don’t cost any money. 

You must apply for your camping permit 30 days before your desired visit. There is also a quota on the Cottonwood Pass Trail from the end of June to mid September. You only need a permit if you stay overnight, but not for day hikes.

In all honesty, Sequoia National Park is slightly smaller and more competitive to enter during quota season. If you crave mountain views and high-elevation hikes, to challenge yourself or to see the world from a whole new angle, then you should know that Sequoia National Park includes parts of the High Sierras. You can visit a unique variety of landscapes if you choose to visit here instead, 

But if you miss out on the backpacking permit for Sequoia National Park for the times you want to visit, then try for a permit for Sequoia National Forest. You’ll see a lot of the same gorgeous country – minus those High Sierras.

Can I Backpack through Sequoia National Park and Kings Canyon on the Same Backpacking Trip?
Photo credit Lara Kaylor
The ownership of the parks is combined, so you don’t need an additional permit to visit Kings Canyon National Park, and there’s no limited entry at any point between the regions. 

The whole area spans 865,964 acres, so depending on how much time you have to spend in the vast wilderness, you could cover as much of the Sequoia and Kings Canyon National Parks as you physically capable. 

Conclusion

Whether you combine your trip with mountainous hikes, rolling meadows, or dense woodland, we hope this guide helps you plan your trip with less stress, so you can focus on the most important part of your backpacking trip — the journey. 

At Pathloom, we believe planning your backpacking trip shouldn’t feel like a part time job. You hit the trails to relax and ease stress, so trip planning shouldn’t add stress to your life.

That’s why we’re creating an all-in-one trip planning app specifically for backpackers. Pathloom helps you discover trails, plan your itinerary, get permits, and receive real-time alerts while on the trail. All from one app. 

And we want you to get it first. 

Register as a Trailblazer today, answer some questions that help us understand your needs, and receive early access when the Pathloom App hits the app store.

Register as a Trailblazer

Recent Posts
See All
How to Make DIY Backpacking Meals You'll Love
How to Get the Elusive Yosemite Backpacking Permits for the Trip of a Lifetime
Is Your Backpacking Emergency Kit Up to Date?</content>
    <images>
      <image>https://static.wixstatic.com/media/nsplsh_e3438a0b35b04460989fe1be3498e4bb~mv2.jpg/v1/fill/w_147,h_184,al_c,q_80,usm_0.66_1.00_0.01,blur_2,enc_auto/nsplsh_e3438a0b35b04460989fe1be3498e4bb~mv2.jpg</image>
      <image>https://static.wixstatic.com/media/nsplsh_5f5878c2edc246b297c2729628d108f5~mv2.jpg/v1/fill/w_147,h_98,al_c,q_80,usm_0.66_1.00_0.01,blur_2,enc_auto/nsplsh_5f5878c2edc246b297c2729628d108f5~mv2.jpg</image>
      <image>https://static.wixstatic.com/media/nsplsh_432d5efafc2e4203ab95734a82fe8780~mv2.jpg/v1/fill/w_147,h_110,al_c,q_80,usm_0.66_1.00_0.01,blur_2,enc_auto/nsplsh_432d5efafc2e4203ab95734a82fe8780~mv2.jpg</image>
      <image>https://static.wixstatic.com/media/167d54_b6adc762c64f47198ba9e53a1aa93915~mv2.png/v1/fill/w_740,h_494,al_c,q_90,usm_0.66_1.00_0.01,enc_auto/167d54_b6adc762c64f47198ba9e53a1aa93915~mv2.png</image>
      <image>https://static.wixstatic.com/media/167d54_4f69cf153e594b80adacc2b1e7569043~mv2.jpg/v1/fill/w_288,h_162,al_c,q_80,enc_auto/167d54_4f69cf153e594b80adacc2b1e7569043~mv2.jpg</image>
      <image>https://static.wixstatic.com/media/nsplsh_584e6679614142434c4a6b~mv2_d_8235_5490_s_4_2.jpg/v1/fill/w_288,h_162,al_c,q_80,enc_auto/nsplsh_584e6679614142434c4a6b~mv2_d_8235_5490_s_4_2.jpg</image>
      <image>https://static.wixstatic.com/media/bb4f73_1637abe4242841ef967144f918017ce2~mv2.jpeg/v1/fill/w_288,h_162,al_c,q_80,enc_auto/bb4f73_1637abe4242841ef967144f918017ce2~mv2.jpeg</image>
      <image>https://static.wixstatic.com/media/f84b209469da4471b60850dc411d770b.jpg/v1/fill/w_1250,h_428,al_c,q_85,usm_1.20_1.00_0.01,enc_auto/f84b209469da4471b60850dc411d770b.jpg</image>
      <image>https://static.wixstatic.com/media/81af6121f84c41a5b4391d7d37fce12a.png/v1/fill/w_24,h_24,al_c,q_85,usm_1.20_1.00_0.01,enc_auto/81af6121f84c41a5b4391d7d37fce12a.png</image>
      <image>https://static.wixstatic.com/media/203dcdc2ac8b48de89313f90d2a4cda1.png/v1/fill/w_24,h_24,al_c,q_85,usm_1.20_1.00_0.01,enc_auto/203dcdc2ac8b48de89313f90d2a4cda1.png</image>
      <image>https://static.wixstatic.com/media/7528824071724d12a3e6c31eee0b40d4.png/v1/fill/w_24,h_24,al_c,q_85,usm_1.20_1.00_0.01,enc_auto/7528824071724d12a3e6c31eee0b40d4.png</image>
    </images>
  </blog>
</blogs>